Finding Aid for Office of the Vice President for Research (University of Michigan), Records, 1950-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Office of the Vice-President for Research (University of Michigan) records
1950-2010
University of Michigan. Office of the Vice-President for Research.
87258 Bimu B6 2 UBImul B6
Officially established in 1959, the Office of the Vice-President for Research (OVPR) supports and administers large interdisciplinary projects called research centers and administers research institutes. The record group includes individual vice president's files, central office files, staff files, financial records, administrative files, committee and task force documents and reports, special event files, and project and institute files.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
276 linear feet
1 oversize volumes
The record group (Donor 5123 ) was received in 1981. Periodic accessions to continue.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
University records are public records and once fully processed are generally open to research use. Records that contain personally identifiable information will be restricted in order to protect individual privacy. Certain administrative records are restricted in accordance with university policy as outlined below. The restriction of university records is subject to compliance with applicable laws, including the Freedom of Information Act.
The Vice President for Research record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Records - Box 105-107, 109, 128, 129, 137, 181, 191, 266, 276
Patient/Client Records - Box 106, 122, 133, 144
Executive Officers Records -- Boxes 107-275
After World War II the burden of overseeing the university's rapidly expanding research programs fell upon the Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies. The dean's broad responsibility for research activity was formally acknowledged in 1959 when Dean Ralph A. Sawyer was given the additional title of Vice President for Research (VPR). The Office of the Vice President for research (OVPR) supports and administers large interdisciplinary projects called research centers and also administers research institutes. Research projects which have been overseen by the VPR include the Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project, which provides beneficial uses for atomic energy; the Institute of Science and Technology (IST), which managed large research projects that did not fit into the existing academic structure; and the Institute for Social Research (ISR), which undertakes substantial programs in survey research, political behavior, and other areas.
For practical reasons, the University of Michigan Research Institute (UMRI) was assigned to aid Sawyer in carrying out the administrative tasks of the VPR. The administrative relationship between the VPR and UMRI was formalized in 1961 with UMRI becoming the Office of Research Administration. The function of the Office of Research Administration is to assist faculty members in obtaining support for their research projects and to maintain appropriate records of university research projects. In 1972 the ORA became the Division of Research Development and Administration (DRDA).
At the time of Dean Sawyer's retirement, in 1964, a decision was made to separate the vice presidency from the deanship. Arthur Geoffrey Norman, a professor of botany at Michigan since 1952 and director of the university's botanical gardens since 1955, was named to replace Sawyer as vice president. Some of the problems facing the new VPR were recovering indirect costs of large research programs, integrating research with instructional programs, and developing interdisciplinary research.
During the early 1960s much of the work of the OVPR was involved in overseeing the expansion of government funded research. The majority of sponsored research funds went to engineering and scientific research projects, but as the decade advanced more research funds were received by the social and health sciences. Prior to 1966/67 sponsored research funds had increased an average of 13% to 14% a year, but from 1966 to 1968 a rise of only 5% was reported. By 1968/69 sponsored research had reached a plateau. This was caused in part by a leveling of federal funds and because available faculty time and research space had reached a saturation point.
Classified research policy was a topic of great debate during the late 1960s and early 1970s. A new policy was put into effect in 1968 and then revised in 1972. The 1972 revision prohibits research activities, the foreseeable result of which is to destroy or incapacitate human life, and restrictions that limit open publication of results beyond one year. Interpretation of the new policy resulted in the Willow Run Laboratories disassociating itself from the university, since the majority of university classified research occurred there.
In 1972, although he continued to perform various tasks within OVPR, Norman retired from the vice presidency. He was succeeded by Charles G. Overberger, who had joined the University of Michigan faculty in 1967 and was then chairman of the Chemistry Department. During Overberger's tenure in OVPR, research expenditures increased only 2.4% when adjusted for inflation during the 1970s. In the 1979/80 academic year the distribution of sponsored research funds was 43.3% life sciences, 20% engineering, 16.7% social sciences, 8.9% physical sciences, 1.3% humanities, and 9.8% other.
Overberger resigned in 1983. Rather than seek an immediate replacement, a major study was authorized to determine if the 1964 decision to separate the vice presidency from the deanship of the graduate school should be reversed. While the study was underway, Alfred A. Sussman was named interim VPR while also continuing in his position as Dean of the Graduate School. Eventually it was concluded that the two posts would remain separate, and in 1985 Linda S. Wilson was named vice president for research. Wilson resigned in 1989 and William C. Kelley became interim vice president. In 1990 he became the permanent vice president for research.
Vice Presidents for Research
1959-1964 Ralph A. Sawyer
1964-1972 A. Geoffrey Norman
1972-1983 Charles G. Overberger
1983-1985 Alfred A. Sussman (acting)
1985-1989 Linda S. Wilson
1989-1990 William C. Kelly (acting)
1990-1993 William C. Kelly
1993-1996 Homer Neal
1996-1998 Frederick C. Niedhart
1999-2005 Fawwaz Ulaby
2005 Stephen R. forrest
The records of the vice-president for research date from 1950 to 2001 and measure 179 linear feet. The records document the activities of the office overseeing grant funded research at the University of Michigan and offer some insight into the range of research undertaken at the university. Records include administrative files of vice-presidents, including correspondence, memoranda, and budgetary material relating to research projects and grants of university units and departments; and photographs.
The organization of the records, particularly the early accessions, reflects the tenure of the successive vice presidents for research. Later accessions included files of associate vice-presidents and senior staff officers as well topically organized files that spanned the tenure of several vice presidents. The records are organized into the following series:
A. Geoffrey Newman -- Boxes 1-15, 70-71
Charles Overberger -- Boxes 15-69
Charles Overberger/Warren Sussman -- Boxes 72-87
Linda S. Wilson,-- Boxes 88-100
William C. Kelly -- Boxes 102-105
Central Files -- Boxes 108-127
OVPR Staff Files -- Boxes 128-134
Julie Ellison -- Boxes 135-136
Marvin Parnes -- Boxes 137-146
OVPR Financial and Administrative Files -- Boxes 147-148
Administrative Files -- Boxes 149-150
Committees and Task forces -- 151-164
Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project and Ford Nuclear Reactor -- Boxes 165 --166
Special Events, Symposiums, and Promotional -- Boxes 167-170
Presidential Initiatives Fund -- Boxes 171-179
Subjects:
Argonne University Associates.; Association of American Universities. Council on Federal Relations.; College publications.; Institute for Defense Analyses.; Middle English dictionary.; University of Michigan. Computing Center.; University of Michigan. Dental Research Institute.; University of Michigan. Division of Research Development and Administration.; University of Michigan. Highway Safety Research Institute.; University of Michigan. Institute for Social Research.; University of Michigan. Institute of Science and Technology.; Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project.; University of Michigan. Unit for Laboratory Animal Medicine.; University of Michigan. Office of the Vice-President for Research.; University of Michigan. Willow Run Laboratories.; University Research Association.; Norman, A. G. (Arthur Geoffrey), 1905-1982; Sussman, Alfred S.; Overberger, C. G. (Charles Gilbert), 1920-; Wilson, Linda.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Prints.; Computers.; Construction industry.; Crosby, Elizabeth Caroline, 1888-; Great Lakes.; Lasers.; Norman, A. G. (Arthur Geoffrey), 1905-1982; Photographs.; Regents Plaza (University of Michigan); Research facilities--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Buildings.; University of Michigan--Campus.; University of Michigan. Institute for Social Research.; University of Michigan--Research.; Lauersdorf, R. (Robin)
- A. Geoffrey Norman, 1958-1972
  The A. Geoffrey Norman series dates from 1958 to 1972 and has been divided into three sub-series, Correspondence, General File, and Consortiums File.
  - Correspondence, 1964-1972
    Correspondence dates from 1964 to 1972 and is arranged chronologically. It is surprisingly frank and substantive, although its arrangement makes it difficult to use.
    - 1964
      - September -December (Box 1)
    - 1965
      - January -February (Box 1)
      - March-April (Box 1)
      - May -June (Box 1)
      - July -August (Box 1)
      - September -October (Box 1)
      - November -December (Box 1)
    - 1966
      - January -February (Box 1)
      - March-April (Box 1)
      - May -June (Box 1)
      - July -August (Box 1)
      - September -October (Box 1)
      - November -December (Box 1)
    - 1967
      - January -February (Box 1)
      - March-April (Box 1)
      - May -June (Box 1)
      - July -August (Box 1)
      - September -October (Box 1)
      - November -December (Box 1)
    - 1968
      - January -February (Box 1)
      - March-April (Box 1)
      - May -June (Box 1)
      - July -August (Box 1)
      - September -October (Box 1)
      - November -December (Box 1)
    - 1969 (Box 2)
      - January -February (Box 2)
      - March-April (Box 2)
      - May -June (Box 2)
      - July -August (Box 2)
      - September -October (Box 2)
      - November -December (Box 2)
    - 1970
      - January -February (Box 2)
      - March-April (Box 2)
      - May -June (Box 2)
      - July -August (Box 2)
      - September -October (Box 2)
      - November -December (Box 2)
    - 1971
      - January -February (Box 2)
      - March-April (Box 2)
      - May -June (Box 2)
      - July -August (Box 2)
      - September -October (Box 2)
      - November -December (Box 2)
    - 1972
      - January -February (Box 2)
      - March-April (Box 2)
      - May -June (Box 2)
      - July -August (Box 2)
  - General Files
    The General File subseries is composed of two sub-units, the Reference Files and the Research Support/Interest File. Reference (1958-1972) dates primarily from 1964 to 1972. It is arranged alphabetically using a combination of institutional titles and subject headings. Its overall quality is uneven, being detailed in some areas but cursory in others. Well documented areas include the Computing Center, the Dental Research Institute, the Highway Safety Research Institute and Indirect Costs. the Research Support/Interest File (1961-1972) documents agencies, corporations, or individuals which funded or had the potential to fund research activities. Included here for convenience are agencies of the federal government, although the vice-president's office originally maintained these as a separate file.
    Additional General File material was received in 1986 consisting primarily of Classified Research Committee files and Research Policy Committee minutes. These records are housed in boxes 70 and 71.
    - Reference, 1958-1972
      - Academic Affairs
        - Advisory Council Minutes, 1972 (Box 3)
        - Office of, 1966-1972 (Box 3)
      - Accounting, 1970 (Box 3)
      - Administrative Systems, (C.J. Walter), 1965-1970 (Box 3)
      - Aerospace Engineering Department (High Altitude Laboratory), 1964-1971 (Box 3)
      - AMOS Project, 1966-1967 (Box 3)
      - Amphibian Facility (George W. Nace), 1967-1972 (Box 3)
      - Animal Facilities, 1964-1972 (Box 3)
      - Anthropology, 1967-1971 (Box 3)
      - Architecture and Design, 1966-1972 (Box 3)
      - Art (Museum and Department), 1966-1972 (Box 3)
      - Astronomy Department, 1966-1971 (Box 3)
      - Benninghoff, William S., 1966-1972 (Box 3)
      - Bioengineering, 1964-1969 (Box 3)
      - Biological Chemistry Department, 1970-1971 (Box 3)
      - Biological Sciences, General Committee re Division of, 1964-1965 (Box 3)
      - Biological Station, 1965-1972 (Box 3)
      - Botanical Gardens
        - Director Search, 1965-1966 (Box 3)
        - General, 1966-1971 (Box 3)
      - Botany Department, 1964-1972 (Box 3)
      - Budget
        - 1969/70, 1970/71 (Box 3)
        - 1971/72 (Box 3)
      - Business Administration, School of, 1964-1971 (Box 3)
      - Business Operations (James F. Brinkerhoff), 1967-1969 (Box 3)
      - Cancer Research Center Committee, 1971-1972 (Box 3)
      - Career, Career Development and Research Scientist Awards, 1965-1972 (Box 3)
      - Cellular Biology, 1964-1970 (Box 3)
      - Centers
        - Miscellaneous, 1968-1969 (Box 3)
        - Afro-American and African, 1970 (Box 3)
        - Ancient and Modern Studies, Coordination of, 1967-1971 (Box 3)
        - Chinese Studies, 1970 (Box 3)
        - Early Childhood Development and Education, 1972 (Box 3)
        - Human Growth and Development, 1969-1971 (Box 3)
        - Political Studies, 1970-1971 (Box 3)
        - Population Planning, 1968 (Box 3)
        - Population Studies, 1966-1971 (Box 3)
        - Research on Conflict Resolution, 1968-1971 (Box 3)
        - Research on Language and Language Behavior
          - Executive Committee, 1965-1969 (Box 3)
          - General, 1964-1971 (Box 3)
        - Research on Learning and Teaching, 1966-1971 (Box 4)
        - Research on Macromolecules, 1968-1971 (Box 4)
        - Research on Social Organization, 1972 (Box 4)
        - Study of Higher Education, 1966-1972 (Box 4)
        - Western European Studies, 1969-1970 (Box 4)
      - Chemical and Metallurgical Engineering, 1966-1970 (Box 4)
      - Chemistry Department, 1964-1972 (Box 4)
      - Classical Studies, 1967 (Box 4)
      - Classified Research Overview Panel (excluding Willow Run Laboratories), 1972 (Box 4)
      - Communication Sciences Department, 1966-1970 (Box 4)
      - Computer Inventory (National Science Foundation), 1971 (Box 4)
      - Computing Center
        - Ad Hoc Computing Advisory Committee, 1964-1965 (Box 4)
        - Allocations for Computing Services, 1968-1971 (Box 4)
        - Budget, 1970 (Box 4)
        - Determination of Charges, 1970 (Box 4)
        - Executive Committee, 1959-1972 (Box 4)
        - Financial Status, 1960-1964 (Box 4)
        - Funding, ca. 1970-, circa 1972 (Box 4)
        - General, 3 folders (Box 4)
        - University Committee on Computer Policy and Utilization, circa 1966-1972; 3 folders (Box 4)
        - University Committee on Computer Policy and Utilization, circa 1966-1972 (Box 5)
        - Use of IBM Time, 1959-1964 (Box 5)
        - Users Group (CCUG), 1970-1971 (Box 5)
      - Conductron, 1971 (Box 5)
      - Conflicts of Interest, 1965-1968 (Box 5)
      - Controller (Matthews, C.W.), 1965-1971 (Box 5)
      - Cooley Electronics Laboratory, 1966-1970 (Box 5)
      - Cutler, Richard L. (Urban Affairs), 1968-1970 (Box 5)
      - Cyclotron Building Remodeling Project, 1966-1971 (Box 5)
      - Dental Research Institute
        - General, 1971-1972 (Box 5)
        - Policy Committee, 1965-1972 (Box 5)
        - Scientific Advisory Committee, 1968-1972 (Box 5)
      - Dentistry, School of, 1965-1971 (Box 5)
      - Economics Department, 1968-1970 (Box 5)
      - Education, School of, 1966-1971 (Box 5)
      - Edwards, Ward (Oregon Research Institute), 1967-1971 (Box 5)
      - Electrical Engineering, Department of, 1964-1972 (Box 5)
      - ENACT (Environmental Action for Survival), 1969-1970 (Box 5)
      - Engineering, College of, 1965-1972 (Box 5)
      - Environmental Programs, Committee on, 1971 (Box 5)
      - Environmental Simulation Laboratory, 1967-1971 (Box 5)
      - Executive Officers (of University)
        - Minutes of Meetings, 1968-1971; 2 folders (Box 5)
        - Miscellaneous, 1967-1971 (Box 6)
      - Extension Service, 1965-1968 (Box 6)
      - Faculty
        - Awards, 1966-1972 (Box 6)
        - Compensation, (U.S.-University Dispute), 1965; 1967 (Box 6)
        - Effort Reports, 1965-1970 (Box 6)
        - Reform Coalition, 1971 (Box 6)
      - Fauri, Fedele F. (vice-president), 1968-1971 (Box 6)
      - Fleming, Robben W.
        - General, 1967-1972 (Box 6)
        - Responses for, 1969-1972 (Box 6)
      - Flint College, 1965-1972 (Box 6)
      - Forest Service Fire Research Laboratory, 1967 (Box 6)
      - Franken, Peter A., 1965-1967 (Box 6)
      - Geology and Mineralogy, 1968-1971 (Box 6)
      - Gifts Receiving Office, 1968-1971 (Box 6)
      - Graduate Assembly, 1971 (Box 6)
      - Graduate School, 1965-1972 (Box 6)
      - Graduate Student Assistantship Program, 1971 (Box 6)
      - Great Lakes Resource Management Program, 1972 (Box 6)
      - H Miscellaneous, 1965-1971 (Box 6)
      - Hardships, 1964-1971 (Box 6)
      - Harris-Moyers Dispute (Center for Human Growth and Development), 1970-1972 (Box 6)
      - Health, Education and Welfare, Department of, Discrimination Agreement, 1971 (Box 6)
      - Highway Safety Research Institute
        - Executive Committee, 1966-1972 (Box 6)
        - General, 1965-1972; 2 folders (Box 6)
        - Liaison Committee, 1967 (Box 6)
        - Operations, 1968-1971 (Box 6)
      - Hospital Administration, Bureau of, 1965-1967 (Box 6)
      - Human Subjects Committees, 1966-1972 (Box 6)
      - I Miscellaneous, 1968-1972 (Box 7)
      - Indirect Costs
        - Audits, 1968-1969 (Box 7)
        - Computation, 1967-1971 (Box 7)
        - Cost Sharing, 1965-1971 (Box 7)
        - General, 1965-1966 (Box 7)
        - National Science Foundation Ceiling, 1968 (Box 7)
        - Negotiations
          - 1968 (Box 7)
          - 1969-1970 (Box 7)
          - 1970-1971 (Box 7)
        - Reimbursement Rates, 1966-1972 (Box 7)
        - Reimbursement Report, 1971-1972 (Box 7)
      - Infrared and Optics Laboratory, 1968-1970 (Box 7)
      - Institute for Public Policy Studies, 1972 (Box 7)
      - Institute for Social Research
        - General, 1965-1970; 2 folders (Box 7)
        - Survey Research Center, 1964-1970 (Box 7)
      - Institute for the Study of Mental Retardation and Related Disabilities, 1968-1972 (Box 7)
      - Institute of Environmental Health and Industrial Health, 1966-1971 (Box 7)
      - Institute of Labor and Industrial Relations, 1966-1970 (Box 7)
      - Institute of Medicinal Chemistry, 1964-1970 (Box 7)
      - Institute of Science and Technology
        - General, 1964-1972 (Box 7)
        - Great Lakes Research Institute, 1964-1972 (Box 7)
      - International Workshop on Earth Resources Survey Systems, 1970-1971 (Box 8)
      - Interuniversity Consortium for Political Research, 1966-1970 (Box 8)
      - Kahn, Reuben L., 1967 (Box 8)
      - Keeweenaw Rocket Launch Site, 1964-1970 (Box 8)
      - Kennedy, Richard L., 1968-1971 (Box 8)
      - Law School, 1964-1971 (Box 8)
      - Lease-Back Facility on North Campus, 1965 (Box 8)
      - Library, 1967-1971 (Box 8)
      - Linguistics Department, 1966-1972 (Box 8)
      - Literature, Science and the Arts, College of, 1964-1972 (Box 8)
      - MacNee Committee (Willow Run Laboratories), 1969-1970 (Box 8)
      - Macromolecular Research Center Executive Committee, 1969-1972 (Box 8)
      - Mathematics Department, 1966-1970 (Box 8)
      - Medical School, 1965-1972 (Box 8)
      - Mental Health Research Institute, 1965-1972 (Box 8)
      - Meteorology and Oceanography, 1966-1971 (Box 8)
      - Michigan Daily, 1964-1970 (Box 8)
      - Military, 1966 (Box 8)
      - Museums, 1966-1972 (Box 8)
      - Music, School of, 1968-1970 (Box 8)
      - Natural Resources, 1965-1972 (Box 8)
      - Naval Architecture and Marine Engineering, 1968-1971 (Box 8)
      - Neuroscience Building, 1968-1970 (Box 8)
      - Norman, A. Geoffrey, memos from, 1969-1972 (Box 8)
      - Nursing School, 1967-1970 (Box 8)
      - Off-Campus Projects, 1968 (Box 8)
      - Office of Research Administration
        - Editorial Office, 1966-1971 (Box 8)
        - General, 1966-1972 (Box 8)
        - Support of Research Activities, 1969-1972 (Box 8)
      - Opportunity Award Program, 1964-1968 (Box 8)
      - Overruns, 1964-1970 (Box 8)
      - Overtime Compensation, 1966-1968 (Box 8)
      - P Miscellaneous, 1967-1972 (Box 8)
      - Page Charges, 1966-1967 (Box 8)
      - Patent and Invention Policy, 1965-1972 (Box 8)
      - Personnel, 1972 (Box 8)
      - Pharmacy, College of, 1965-1972 (Box 8)
      - Phoenix Project
        - Buildings
          - Catherine St. Laboratory, 1960-1961 (Box 8)
          - Radiation Facility, 1958-1961 (Box 8)
        - Campaign Committee, 1960-1961 (Box 8)
        - Executive Committee, 1965-1972 (Box 9)
        - General, 1964-1972; 3 folders (Box 9)
      - Physics, 1966-1972 (Box 9)
      - Pierpont, W.K. (vice-president and chief financial officer), 1965-1972 (Box 9)
      - Population Research Program, 1970-1971 (Box 9)
      - Professional and Administrative Staff, 1971-1972 (Box 9)
      - Proprietary Research, 1971 (Box 9)
      - Proton Accelerator (2 folders, 1965-1966 (Box 9)
      - Psychology Department, 1965-1971 (Box 9)
      - Public Health, School of, 1964-1972 (Box 9)
      - Radiation Control Service, 1965-1972 (Box 9)
      - Radiation Laboratory, 1965-1970 (Box 9)
      - Regents
        - General, 1965-1972 (Box 9)
        - Requests, 1968-1972 (Box 9)
      - Remote Sensing Symposium, 1968 (Box 9)
      - Research
        - Biological and Chemical Research Controversy (military weapons), 1966-1969 (Box 10)
        - Development Group, 1969-1970 (Box 10)
        - General, 1964-1971 (Box 10)
        - Personnel, 1965-1969 (Box 10)
        - Resource Allocation Committee, 1971-1972 (Box 10)
        - Sea Grant Program
          - Administrative Committee, 1971 (Box 10)
          - Budgets, 1971 (Box 10)
          - General, 1966-1972; 2 folders (Box 10)
        - Security (classified information), 1964-1972 (Box 10)
        - Singer Company (proposed purchase of Willow Run Laboratories), 1970 (Box 10)
        - Social Work, School of, 1966-1972 (Box 10)
        - Space Inventory, 1970-1972 (Box 10)
        - Space Research. Building, 1965-1971 (Box 10)
        - Speech and Hearing Camp, 1968-1969 (Box 10)
        - Sponsored Research Business Office, 1964-1972 (Box 10)
        - Standard Practice Guide, 1969-1970 (Box 10)
        - Stanford and MIT, Incidents and Reports, 1969-1970 (Box 10)
        - Statistical Research Laboratory Executive Committee, 1968-1969 (Box 10)
        - Stroke, George W., 1964-1967 (Box 10)
        - Student
          - Advisory Committee to Vice-President for Research, 1967 (Box 10)
          - Affairs, 1968-1972 (Box 10)
          - Judiciary, 1969-1970 (Box 10)
          - Publications, Board in Control of, 1967-1971 (Box 10)